<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://boblou.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://boblou.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-11T09:01:59-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bob Lou</title><subtitle>Robert &quot;Bob&quot; Lou, MD is a product manager at Google Cloud Healthcare and Life Sciences. This is his personal blog and website.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Vacuous Truth</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2019/11/20/vacuous-truth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Vacuous Truth" /><published>2019-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2019/11/20/vacuous-truth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2019/11/20/vacuous-truth.html">&lt;p&gt;The vacuous truth, a logic concept and not a nihilistic one, refers to a statement that is true because it is a statement about nothing. In my high school, there was a joke that our football team was the best in the state, the joke being that we had no football team. Another example is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All the pigs in the sky are purple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a statement is true because there are no pigs in the sky. In fact, any color or property could replace purple and the statement would still be true. Thus we can also have the true statement: All the pigs in the sky are not purple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems strange that both statements could be true simultaneously, but there is some rationale to this; it is &lt;em&gt;logic&lt;/em&gt; after all. Consider the general statement: All &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; are &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;. The statement’s negation is: There exists an &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; that is not &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;. One can see that if the former statement is true, then the latter must be false, and vica versa. Thus, the negation of our original statement is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There exists a pig in the sky that is not purple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, this is false, and thus the original statement about all pigs in the sky being purple must be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explanation seems reasonable, but perhaps not entirely satisfying. Let us consider a more practical example of a vacuous truth. Suppose I have a website that demands, for some reason, a user’s password be in all caps. Furthermore, suppose that this website is not a great one, and so I was able to create an account despite accidentally leaving the password field blank. Then we must ask, does a blank password satisfy the property of being in all caps. Well yes, but vacuously so. It certainly does not contain any non-capital characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us consider a more realistic website that requires a user’s password contain a capital letter. When I try to create an account with a blank password, the website gives me an error that there is not a capital letter in my password.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, I have a password that is in all caps, yet does not contain a capital letter. Such a statement is illogical, and yet logical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar logical curiosity is the conditional operation, A→B, which can be read, “if A, then B.” The intuitive interpretation is that if A is true, then B must also be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If it is raining, then there are clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could also say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Clouds are necessary for rain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rain is sufficient for clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is not raining or there are clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can check all scenarios and see that the four statements are equivalent.
But consider the following conditional statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If pigs fly, then I am a wizard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If pigs fly, then I am not a wizard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since “pigs fly” is false, the statement is true regardless of the clause following “then.” Thus both statements above are true, though it may seem contradictory. Such statements are vacuous: the “then” clause never obtains, because the “if” clause is always false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I leave the reader to consider whether the following is true or false:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If pigs fly, then pigs do not fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="logic" /><category term="math" /><summary type="html">The vacuous truth, a logic concept and not a nihilistic one, refers to a statement that is true because it is a statement about nothing. In my high school, there was a joke that our football team was the best in the state, the joke being that we had no football team. Another example is,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EpiPen Price Hikes, PBMs, and ERISA</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2019/10/12/epipenpricing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EpiPen Price Hikes, PBMs, and ERISA" /><published>2019-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2019/10/12/epipenpricing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2019/10/12/epipenpricing.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;class-action-lawsuit-against-mylan&quot;&gt;Class Action Lawsuit against Mylan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2007, list price increases have been an annual constant in the world of EpiPen sales. Mylan acquired the exclusive rights to EpiPen in 2007 when the list price of a 2-pack was $93.88. That price skyrocketed to $608.61 by 2016, a CAGR of 23%. However, over the same time period, the cost to produce a 2-pack remained relatively consistent at around $70. In a class action lawsuit, EpiPen users contend that this increase in price was thus caused by Pharmaceutical Benefit Managers (PBMs) inducing and/or colluding with Mylan to increase list prices for their own financial benefit. The plaintiffs claim that market consolidation, closed formularies, and an opaque rebates system were tools used by the PBMs to drive up list prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial step in their logic is that PBMs consolidated to gain power over other players in the value chain. As of the case filing, the four largest PBMs controlled access for 81% of the total retail prescription drug market. The plaintiffs argue this oligopoly power gave PBMs the leverage to manipulate the market to their benefit. Once PBMs secured a sufficiently large portion of the market, they then began using closed formularies to give themselves enormous control over the financial success or failure of prescription drugs. Closed formularies allowed PBMs to steer their member’s pharmacy dollars to a drug of their choosing, and failure to be included on a PBM’s formulary could result in massive market share loss for a pharmaceutical manufacturer. This gave PBMs a new tool to strong-arm manufacturers into offering attractive incentives to PBMs to ensure that their drug was the primary drug included on the formulary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceutical manufacturers needed to find a way to remain in good standing with the PBMs, and they did this by paying them substantial kickbacks in the form of rebates. For each prescription sold, the PBMs received a portion of the revenue by retaining an undisclosed share of the rebates that manufacturers gave off of the list price of their drugs. These revenues were material and account for 37% of Express Scripts’ net receivables in 2017. The combined effects of closed formularies and rebates created a ‘pay-to-play’ system in the drug market. To ensure that their products would continue to receive favorable placements on the PBM formularies, Mylan continuously increased the list price of EpiPen. The document alleges that these price hikes were primarily done to benefit the PBMs, and they argue that PBMs actually want a higher list price since that means they can extract a higher rebate. The plaintiffs argue that the high share of price increases offset by increased rebates (77% in 2015) proves that the primary beneficiaries are the PBMs. Since PBMs refuse to disclose how much total rebate they receive and how much of that rebate is passed through to insurance companies, the plaintiffs conclude that the PBMs must pocket a significant portion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their logic concludes that PBMs induced Mylan to increase the list price of EpiPen by threatening to take away market access for their drug. PBMs’ profits increased dramatically due to these list price increases, while individual consumers were hurt financially since their deductibles and coinsurance rates were based on this increasingly high list price. These actions violate PBM’s fiduciary duties as detailed in ERISA § 404,406.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;are-the-allegations-true&quot;&gt;Are The Allegations True?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each logic step for this complaint is based on a core underlying assumption: the actions of the PBMs were made because of malicious greed and the rising list price of EpiPen would not have been possible under normal market incentives. In other words, if the PBMs would have taken these actions without colluding with Mylan, then the substantial increases in list prices could be simply the result of misaligned market incentives. While complete refutation of this claim is difficult given PBMs’ extreme lack of transparency,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; there are strong reasons to believe that a list price increase was not the result of collusion or PBM-induced changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pbm-consolidation-and-use-of-exclusive-formularies&quot;&gt;PBM Consolidation and Use of Exclusive Formularies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Market consolidation and exclusive formularies are useful bargaining tools to help drive down drug prices–without them PBMs would functionally only have bulk discounts, significantly reducing their negotiating power. Exclusive formularies are a powerful weapon for PBMs to lower drug prices, especially for drugs which have a clinically interchangeable equivalent. Exclusive formularies force drug manufacturers to compete on price in order to be included on said formularies. Thus it is logical for PBMs to consolidate to maintain exclusive formularies and thus have the market power to lower drug prices. Therefore, consolidation by PBMs is an expected result and does not imply intent to use that power for malicious greed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, there were clinically interchangeable equivalents to EpiPen: Sanofi’s Auvi-Q and Adrenaclick, a generic. CVS Caremark, Express Scripts, Prime, and Optum excluded Adrenaclick and to a lesser extent, Auvi-Q, supposedly in an effort to reduce EpiPen’s price. However, Auvi-Q was taken off the market for dosing concerns and EpiPen was 90% of the market. Given the limited alternatives, PBMs may have felt obligated to include EpiPen on their formularies. If EpiPen was the prevailing epinephrine injector, then it is unclear how much power exclusive formularies represented. Even if PBMs had power in excluding Adrenaclick, PBMs allege that they used this power to lower prices for EpiPen. That the PBMs wielded immense negotiating power through exclusive formularies is not sufficient evidence for greed at the expense of patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;increasing-rebates&quot;&gt;Increasing Rebates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plaintiffs in the case argue that the main reason PBMs work for higher rebates is to increase their own profit. However, giving PBMs a share of the rebates they negotiate also serves to align their interests with the insurance companies that they serve. In other words, it is a PBM’s job to minimize final drug costs, and they do this by fighting for higher rebates. Showing that a substantial portion of price increases are being offset by rebates does not prove that PBMs are pushing for that increase to profit more; it could simply mean they are doing their job and preventing final drug prices (net prices) from going up. In fact, net price increases were substantially lower than list price increases, indicating that PBMs may actually be playing a positive role for end customers through rebates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question is complicated by the fact that the passthrough rate of rebates to the final payors (individual customers and insurance companies) is not known. If the PBMs kept the majority of these increased rebates for themselves, then there is a stronger argument for why they would induce a higher list price. On the other hand, if the majority of the increased rebates flowed through to the final payors, then there is little reason to believe the PBMs wanted to create a higher list price. An article from 2017 provides a few examples to suggest that PBMs were favoring EpiPen on their formularies at a higher cost to insurers than generic offerings ($438.53 for EpiPen vs $227.52 for generic).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If this information is true, then there is strong reason to believe that PBMs are favoring Mylan due to higher kickbacks. However, it could be that these are isolated cases and net price to insurer was actually lower for EpiPen than generics because of high rebate passthrough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, because PBM contracts are kept secret, the public does not know how much of the rebate is passed on to payors. With only the information that is public today, it is difficult to prove that the PBMs had control in creating and implementing the alleged kickbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;price-hikes-may-be-unrelated-to-pbm-profits&quot;&gt;Price Hikes May Be Unrelated to PBM Profits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plaintiffs allege that PBMs pushed Mylan to increase prices in order to receive higher rebates. However, while prices and rebates increased together, this does not imply that Mylan increased prices to offer higher rebates. The directionality and timeline of price hikes and rebate increases are important for discerning the cause of Mylan’s price hikes. Indeed, Mylan could have increased price without regard to PBMs, and after prices were raised, PBMs reasonably captured as much as they could in rebates to help their insurance companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look to cases beyond EpiPen, data shows changes in drug prices and changes in rebate are not correlated.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Notably, there are examples of drugs that have increased in price while rebates stayed the same or declined, and examples where drug prices have decreased and rebates have increased.  In contradistinction to the plaintiff’s allegations, the data suggests that drug companies generally do not set a higher price in order to offer higher rebates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to note that drug prices by and large have been increasing, and so the price of EpiPen may have increased independently of any PBM action. In the subsequent section, we discuss factors outside of PBMs that may have led to EpiPen’s price increases. Because we can reasonably expect the price of EpiPen to increase, it is difficult to discern the extent to which PBM’s actions have affected EpiPen pricing. Hence, the mere increase in EpiPen price does not support plaintiffs allegation that PBMs induced and/or colluded with Mylan to increases prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other-factors-in-epipen-price-hikes&quot;&gt;Other Factors in EpiPen Price Hikes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EpiPen prices have been increasing for a long time for various reasons, some of which are not related to PBMs.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One factor is the increasing demand of EpiPen, in part facilitated by Mylan lobbying congress to require epinephrine autoinjectors in school. Mylan efforts have also introduced EpiPen in Walt Disney Parks and airplanes.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Total EpiPen sales increased to over $1B in 2015. On a per person basis, a JAMA study reports that prescriptions have remained stable:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; “the annual rate of EpiPen prescription fills per EpiPen patient increased from 1.18 to 1.20 (+1.6%).” Mylan’s successful marketing efforts to portray EpiPen as a necessary medical equipment in public spaces, similar to defibrillators, allows Mylan to increase prices in line with increased demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor is the difficulty competitors are facing in entering the market. At the time of the price hikes, EpiPen had a virtual monopoly with 90% of the market and the auto-injector device is patented. Moreover, patients are unlikely to want to switch to another epinephrine auto-injector, especially if the EpiPen had saved their lives before. A competitor, Teva Pharmaceuticals, failed to gain FDA approval for their epinephrine auto-injector. Sanofi also had difficulty and had to recall its epinephrine auto-injector because of potentially incorrect dosages being delivered. That leaves Mylan with significant pricing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;types-of-insurance-exposing-patients-to-high-oop-costs&quot;&gt;Types of Insurance Exposing Patients to High OOP Costs&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to increasing EpiPen prices, changing coverage policies also play a role in the increasing out-of-pocket costs to patients. With an increasing use of cost-sharing mechanisms by health plans, patients may be financially responsible for more of their prescription costs, particularly with high deductible health plans and high coinsurance plans. A high deductible health plan could expose a patient to the full list price of EpiPen. These high deductible health plans have been on the rise with nearly half of employer-based health insurance subscribers opting for one.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Additionally, some drug manufacturers will offer coupons directly to the patient in order to incentivise the patient to remain loyal to their brand in the face of high deductibles. While these coupons are not allowed for Medicare and Medicaid enrollees, Mylan currently offers a $300 EpiPen rebate for commercially-insured patients.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was written in collaboration with Phil Holsted.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Bringing “Transparent Thinking” to PBM … - Trucker Huss.” 11 Jan. 2019, https://www.truckerhuss.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Bringing-%E2%80%9CTransparent-Thinking%E2%80%9D-to-PBM-Management.pdf. Accessed 5 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Behind the Push to Keep Higher-Priced EpiPen in Consumers ….” 6 Aug. 2017, https://www.wsj.com/articles/behind-the-push-to-keep-higher-priced-epipen-in-consumers-hands-1502036741. Accessed 6 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“https://www.pcmanet.org/infographics/ 0.7 2019-10-30T12:02 ….” https://www.pcmanet.org/sitemap-posttype-page.xml. Accessed 6 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Significant Increases in EpiPen Price - JAMA Network.” 11 Oct. 2016, https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2565728. Accessed 5 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“How Mylan, the maker of EpiPen, became a virtual monopoly ….” 25 Aug. 2016, https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/2016/08/25/7f83728a-6aee-11e6-ba32-5a4bf5aad4fa_story.html. Accessed 6 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Out-of-Pocket Spending Among Commercially Insured ….” 27 Mar. 2017, https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamainternalmedicine/fullarticle/2612114. Accessed 5 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“EpiPen Costs Add to High-Deductible Insurance Woes ….” 12 Sep. 2016, https://www.consumerreports.org/drugs/epipen-costs-add-to-high-deductible-insurance-woes/. Accessed 5 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Access to EpiPen®.” https://www.epipen.com/paying-for-epipen-and-generic. Accessed 6 Nov. 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="medicine" /><summary type="html">Class Action Lawsuit against Mylan Since 2007, list price increases have been an annual constant in the world of EpiPen sales. Mylan acquired the exclusive rights to EpiPen in 2007 when the list price of a 2-pack was $93.88. That price skyrocketed to $608.61 by 2016, a CAGR of 23%. However, over the same time period, the cost to produce a 2-pack remained relatively consistent at around $70. In a class action lawsuit, EpiPen users contend that this increase in price was thus caused by Pharmaceutical Benefit Managers (PBMs) inducing and/or colluding with Mylan to increase list prices for their own financial benefit. The plaintiffs claim that market consolidation, closed formularies, and an opaque rebates system were tools used by the PBMs to drive up list prices.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Restaurant Thoughts: Blue Hill At Stone Barns</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2019/08/21/bluehill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Restaurant Thoughts: Blue Hill At Stone Barns" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2019/08/21/bluehill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2019/08/21/bluehill.html">&lt;p&gt;Blue Hill is more than a restaurant, clearly, given their location on the Stone Barns farm. You can take a tour of the farm where you can see your eventual dinner in the ground. It is a strange juxtaposition of ultra fine dining side suits and all, and sustainability in the form of farm education, whole animal butchery, and vegetable heavy menus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is somewhat disappointing then that on our dinner day, maybe only 15% of guests actually took the farm tour. For most, it seems that Blue Hills is primarily a fancy dinner with some style. Nonetheless, I greatly appreciate their emphasis on produce and the farm tour. The service is pretty impressive with nearly 1:1 staff to diner ratio. The meal itself is a 4 hour experience with a sort of intermission where you go to another part of the restaurant, for example, an outdoor grill. It is a fantastic format that gets you thinking about food. It is as much show as it is food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the number of courses and somewhat curt names of the dish, I wish I could know more about the dishes. Only some dishes really get the whole farm backstory and explanation of why a dish is the way it is, which makes me really want to hear more about the dishes that don’t get that exposition. I had to ask about the dishes to hear more about the ingredients used and so on. I understand that most diners probably do not want all this information for 20+ dishes, but it feels like it is important, especially at a farm-restaurant focused on education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the main course, we were served steak along side a beet, cooked in the style of steak. It was a nice premise–showing how a beet is comparable to a cow’s psoas major, but I think I still got a very standard steak as the main course. Herein lies the tension: Blue Hill is a fine dining establishment catering towards diners who want expensive meats and panache, yet Stone Barns is a farm that cares about sustainability and ecological impact. The disconnect is evident, but Blue Hill does its best to serve both demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, Blue Hill was a fantastic experience. The food, the farm, the tour, and the education were all great. I’m more inclined to cook with produce in my own life. They were effective in communicating their message whilst delivering a spectacular meal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="food" /><summary type="html">Blue Hill is more than a restaurant, clearly, given their location on the Stone Barns farm. You can take a tour of the farm where you can see your eventual dinner in the ground. It is a strange juxtaposition of ultra fine dining side suits and all, and sustainability in the form of farm education, whole animal butchery, and vegetable heavy menus.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s All About Perspective</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2019/03/22/its-all-about-perspective.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It's All About Perspective" /><published>2019-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2019/03/22/its-all-about-perspective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2019/03/22/its-all-about-perspective.html">&lt;p&gt;The photo of a railroad disappearing into the distance at a singular point is a classic image that demonstrates the intuitive notion that farther away objects appear smaller. We can be even more precise and say that the apparent size is directly proportional to the distance, that is, a ten foot tree will appear the same size as a twenty foot tree that is twice as far. Similarly, in the photo, we could count the pixels between the two rails and find a point &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;, where the track has narrowed by 50% compared to point &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;  would indicate a point that is twice as far as &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;. If we knew how far some point in the tracks was, we could calculate the distance of any other point along the tracks, just from a photo. There are other interesting properties to consider in the photo: we a see a singular vanishing point at which the parallel rails converge. I have drawn some boxes with one, two, and three such vanishing points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/perspective.png&quot; alt=&quot;perepective&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first box resembles the railroad track with one vanishing point. The second box’s edges, if extended, will converge to two vanishing points on the left and right. Finally, the third box’s edges converge at three vanishing points. An interesting question to consider is how many vanishing points are possible in a picture?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, consider any two parallel lines in the scene. If they go away from the viewer, they will become smaller and smaller, creating a vanishing point. You could imagine yourself having an infinitely long arm, and wherever you pointed your arm, you would create a vanishing point as your arm disappeared into the distance. Thus, with an infinite number of directions to point your arm, there are infinitely many possible vanishing points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps surprising because the terms &lt;em&gt;one point perspective&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;two point perspective&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;three point perspective&lt;/em&gt; imply that the number of vanishing points is strictly dependent on the position of the viewer. But by placing a railroad track in your scene, you could add another vanishing point and so the number of vanishing points is also scene dependent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine that you are facing a long wall (the wall runs from East to West in front of you and you are facing North). Clearly, the East and West ends of the wall are farther from you than the bit of wall directly in front you, so would the wall appear to taper at the sides? If you photographed such a wall, would the walls be shorter on the sides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images are produced by projecting a scene onto an image plane. In the images we have discussed, distant objects appear smaller, which is true to life. But what if I drew objects such that they always stayed the same size?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/parallelprojection.png&quot; alt=&quot;parallel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four projections in the image. Notably, cubes farther away from the viewer are rendered with the same apparent size. A railroad in these images would not vanish to a point. In fact, we see that all parallel lines are preserved, and so there are no vanishing points. The fact that apparent size does not change with distance means that we could measure objects in the image accurately if we knew some distance in the image. Thus these projection are useful for maps and technical drawing. These projections, save for the top left “oblique” projection, are also equivalent to viewing a scene infinitely far away with infinite zoom. This makes sense as an object 1,000,000 feet away from you and the same object 1,000,000 + 1 feet away from you is only .0001% further away and thus .0001% apparently smaller. Where as an object 1 ft away from you appears half the size 1 + 1 ft away. In photography, zooming in has the effect of “flattening” an image, which we can now formally describe as preserving apparent size despite distance between objects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="math" /><category term="photography" /><summary type="html">The photo of a railroad disappearing into the distance at a singular point is a classic image that demonstrates the intuitive notion that farther away objects appear smaller. We can be even more precise and say that the apparent size is directly proportional to the distance, that is, a ten foot tree will appear the same size as a twenty foot tree that is twice as far. Similarly, in the photo, we could count the pixels between the two rails and find a point x, where the track has narrowed by 50% compared to point y. x would indicate a point that is twice as far as y. If we knew how far some point in the tracks was, we could calculate the distance of any other point along the tracks, just from a photo. There are other interesting properties to consider in the photo: we a see a singular vanishing point at which the parallel rails converge. I have drawn some boxes with one, two, and three such vanishing points.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Restaurant Thoughts: Atomix</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2018/06/29/atomix.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Restaurant Thoughts: Atomix" /><published>2018-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2018/06/29/atomix</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2018/06/29/atomix.html">&lt;p&gt;Atomix is truly a marvelous culinary experience. It is clear that JP and Ellia, the duo at the helm, care deeply about Korean culinary tradition. Their attention to every detail is literally palpable–you can choose the pair chopsticks that you eat with from a beautiful, curated collection. The layout of the restaurant, the aesthetics, the information card that comes with every dish, the uniforms, and every other little thing all bring the dining experience closer to their goal of a “new tomorrow.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to being seated, you are brought to a dimly lit lounge that might as well be from the movie set of the next big budget sci-fi movie. A few snacks are served and then diners are brought to the intimate bar. The waitstaff are dressed in flowing understated t-shirts that make stiff suits feel outdated. The stage is set and it is all very exciting to take in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the food is the most important thing, and they have overwhelmingly succeeded in that regard. A $175 entry fee gets you 10 courses. Given the limited seating and generous portions of uni, caviar, wagyu, and such, the price feels more than fair. Other ingredients include soy sauces sourced from Korea and house milled rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ingredients are cleverly assembled with sound technique. A stand out dish presented eel with eggplant bound together by an intensely savory cream sauce. The flavor is heavy, and the soft eggplant almost seems to become the eel–it tastes amazing. It is a complex dish with lots of prep that I would have not known about if not for the information card that accompanies each dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information cards might seem as overly didactic and perhaps some diners feel that food should speak for itself, but I wholeheartedly appreciated knowing the background of each dish and the full list of ingredients. The waitstaff is knowledgeable and eager to explain any of the more obscure ingredients or techniques. I hope that this becomes more common amongst fine dining establishments. As fine dining is privy to hard to source ingredients and inaccessible techniques, it is important to be transparent about how such things affect a dish. The rarity of an ingredient and the difficulty of a preparation are not themselves praiseworthy. They are laudable only if they benefit the dish in a sensible way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the food, there was a dish or two that contained ingredient combinations that I felt were confusing, such as the bingsu that contained creme fraiche, coriander seed, pepper, and strawberries, but the majority of dishes are superlative, not to mention the banchan and rice pairings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left Atomix in awe and inspired to cook with intention and meticulousness. At least for me, they have achieved their goal of a “new tomorrow.” The highest praise I can give to a restaurant is that they are pushing the boundaries of what food and dining can be, and Atomix certainly does that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="food" /><summary type="html">Atomix is truly a marvelous culinary experience. It is clear that JP and Ellia, the duo at the helm, care deeply about Korean culinary tradition. Their attention to every detail is literally palpable–you can choose the pair chopsticks that you eat with from a beautiful, curated collection. The layout of the restaurant, the aesthetics, the information card that comes with every dish, the uniforms, and every other little thing all bring the dining experience closer to their goal of a “new tomorrow.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recommendation Systems</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2018/05/02/recommendations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recommendation Systems" /><published>2018-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2018/05/02/recommendations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2018/05/02/recommendations.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-recommendation-system&quot;&gt;What is a Recommendation System?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core, a recommendation system is a function that takes user data as input and outputs that user’s predicted rating for a set of products. The process of creating this system is complex and the subject of much research, but an overview will be provided here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acquiring-training-data&quot;&gt;Acquiring Training Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before a machine learning algorithm can be trained, the user data must be collected first. This often takes the form of prior user stated preferences, such as prior ratings or what they clicked on. We can represent these preferences in a utility matrix&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, the matrix is sparse, that is, many entries of the matrix will be empty since the majority of users have provided a preferences on a small fraction of potential product offerings. The goal of the recommendation system is to predict the missing values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, we acquire data on each products features &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X&lt;/script&gt;, for example the price, genre of movie, or color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;training-the-classifier&quot;&gt;Training the Classifier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A variety of classifier algorithms can be used, but for simplicity’s sake, let us use a linear regression. For a given user &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt; we can fit a linear regression from product features &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X&lt;/script&gt; to that user’s rating for that product. These linear regression coefficients, the parameters, give us information about that user’s preference for features. Now we have some information about each user’s preferences in terms of features rather than products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaborative-filtering&quot;&gt;Collaborative Filtering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the prior step gave us a very rudimentary look into the user’s preferences, it does not exploit comparing one user to other users. If  two users preferences are similar to another, we can use that information to predict each other’s preferences. The process by which this is done is called collaborative filtering. First, we define a similarity metric, for example, the cosine distance between their preferences, to quantify the distance between two user’s preferences. We then predict a user’s preferences based on every other user’s preferences, weighted by similarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this is a gross oversimplification with many details and steps, like data pre-processing, having been left out. There are also a litany of other, more involved, methods to perform the same task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predicting customer preferences is practically the essence of marketing, and so there is a wealth of applications in marketing. These systems are ubiquitous and are one of the most successful examples of machine learning in marketing. The most familiar and canonical examples are Netflix’s recommendations that fill a user’s personalized “home page” and Amazon’s recommended products, but nearly every website you use has some form of a recommendation system running, from online dating sites, to research journals, to financial services, and insurance products. Just about everything you can imagine…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-long-tail&quot;&gt;The Long Tail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recommendation system becomes more important as company carries more products. By carrying more products, a company is able to capture the “long tail” of consumer preferences, that is, the products that consumers want that are not the most popular products. A company with only one product can only offer that single product which likely does not meet the complete demands of the market. As the number of differentiated products offered increases, the demands of the market are better met. Physical delivery systems are limited by physical limitations on how many SKUs they can offer, while online systems can offer a far greater number of SKUs. The long tail phenomenon describes the significance of the combined demand for all of the other non-popular SKUs which online systems can provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that online systems can have an immense number of product offerings, for example YouTube offers billions of videos, it is imperative that companies have a computational method of determining what a consumer’s preferences are in order to best recommend a few products among many potential products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;segmentation&quot;&gt;Segmentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some sense, the recommendation system is already a segmentation algorithm, but segmenting every single user into their own segment. Nonetheless, these recommendation systems can also be excellent as a method of clustering. By generating user’s preferences, it is easy to run segmentation algorithms to gain insights about the patterns of customers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="math" /><category term="cs" /><summary type="html">What is a Recommendation System?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Thoughts: Lolita</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2017/09/03/lolita.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Thoughts: Lolita" /><published>2017-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2017/09/03/lolita</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2017/09/03/lolita.html">&lt;p&gt;Unbeknown to me at the time of reading, the sham foreword to Lolita is actually written by Nabokov. The foreword declares that the novel would be a classic in psychiatric circles, and so with my present knowledge of Lolita as a literary classic, the foreword seemed genuine. The foreword is somewhat sympathetic to Humbert in that it acknowledges his atrocities, but praises his ability to describe his love for Lolita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is told from Humbert’s perspective, and this is made apparent by several mechanisms. Perhaps the most apparent is Humbert’s generous generous sprinkling of French, a trait that many characters comment on. He also makes casual references to future events and to names of characters that have not been introduced yet. Charlotte’s death is mentioned nonchalantly, which unnerved me with thoughts of how she would die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Charlotte does die, the story quickly progresses to Humbert and Lolita meandering journey across the States. By the time Lolita is forced to be with Humbert on the road, there are sparse descriptions of Lolita’s emotional state. Humbert writes that Lolita sobs every night for she has absolutely nowhere else to go. This peek into Lolita’s condition combined with the reader’s intense awareness that they are viewing the story from Humbert’s perspective, is nightmarish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the dark storyline, Lolita is written beautifully with memorable descriptions that sometimes bring to mind prior events. Lolita’s Aztec red bathing suit is the same color as one of Trapp’s many automobiles. When Clare Quilty is shot, he rises from his chair like a “mad Nijinsky,” the same Nijinsky that Gaston has an image of in his attic. If you flipped to a random page, you would certainly find an aesthetically appealing example of the English language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a fire opal dissolving within a ripple-ringed pool&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;mock derision at mock wit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;blue sulks and rosey mirths&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lolita was a laborious read for me. Every chapter, of which there are many, was filled with new words, obscure words, and made up words that I felt the need to look up; some phrases, like “diaphragmatic melting,” remain incomprehensible to me. I also do not know French, of which there is quite a bit. Even with my effortful reading, I barely remembered who Clare Quilty was when it was revealed that he was responsible for Lolita’s disappearance, which according to Humbert, “the astute reader has guessed long ago.”
My response is, in Humbert’s words, “Oh Mnemosyne, sweetest and most mischievous of muses.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humbert, near the end of the book, mentions that Humbert is a pseudonym. This implies that in the story, he provided other pseudonyms to hotels, not pseudonyms of his pseudonym, Humbert. Other characters mistakenly called him Humbird, but these events had to have been fabricated by Humberg. Names seem so important in the book: Lolita, Dolores Haze, Dolly Schiller, Lo-lee-ta. And so the end brings a dose of uncertainty to Humbert’s narrative and a reminder that Nabokov fabricated all these levels of meta-fabrication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly, in Nabokov’s closing comments, he mentions Dolly Schiller’s death as a “special delectation” of his, but I’m quite sure this wasn’t actually described in the book. Upon looking the matter up, the only other reference to Lolita’s death is in the foreword…
Nonetheless, I will remember the other various scenes that were rendered so beautifully and how Humbert was able to make transcendent his despicable desires. My thoughts on the book mirror the foreword:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How magically his singing violin can conjure up a tendresse, a compassion for Lolita that makes us entranced with the book while abhorring its author!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="media" /><summary type="html">Unbeknown to me at the time of reading, the sham foreword to Lolita is actually written by Nabokov. The foreword declares that the novel would be a classic in psychiatric circles, and so with my present knowledge of Lolita as a literary classic, the foreword seemed genuine. The foreword is somewhat sympathetic to Humbert in that it acknowledges his atrocities, but praises his ability to describe his love for Lolita.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Problem with Models</title><link href="https://boblou.github.io/2017/08/15/model-problem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Problem with Models" /><published>2017-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://boblou.github.io/2017/08/15/model-problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://boblou.github.io/2017/08/15/model-problem.html">&lt;p&gt;The rules of causality and reason, by which the universe apparently operates, are represented as models. The apparent order of phenomena in reality is condensed into an abstract representation in an attempt to predict and offer insight into reality. However, human actions seem particularly resistant to models. There are a plethora of models postulating the possible nature of human, human’s end, and the nature of societies, but they conflict with each other. Through this dialectic, a new model is made, perhaps closer to the objective truth, but the model, being an entity in the intelligible world and not the sensible world, can never encompass complete objective truth. Though models are undeniably useful in understanding reality, we must consider the limitations of models and the consequences of our models failing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A model is an abstraction of reality, hence necessarily simplified and incomplete. A model represents reality through rules or equations. Every model is limited in that, when we make predictions using a model, we always assume that the future will behave like the past, which cannot be proven. This is particularly true of human interaction as society changes at a rapid pace. Furthermore, when we interpret reality to make our models, we cannot observe all of reality; we often have limited data to base our assumptions upon. Again, this is especially true with human interaction as we do not have a controlled environment. Instead, our data comes from history and hence our assumptions in the model cannot be proven to be true in general. The model is always limited, but it can be a powerful tool for understanding and predicting phenomena. Just as we try to create a standard model of the universe in an attempt to understand and predict physical phenomena, we create a social model in attempt to understand and predict human action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 17th century, many models for society were based upon the individual. The fundamental nature of humans was taken as an assumption, from which social values were derived, for example the Hobbesian state of war, or Locke’s state of nature. The models of society arose from theories of human nature, but the theories of human nature varied widely. In the 19th century, a paradigm shift occurred wherein the state of human nature became dependent on society. Marx famously says, “It is not the consciousness of men which determines their existence; it is on the contrary their social existence which determines their consciousness.” Thus, the nature of man is determined by society. The causal arrows of the model were reversed completely. This nature versus nurture debate relates to Berlin’s notion of positive and negative freedom: the individual can be free from interference and act on his own nature to form society, or the society can nurture the individual to be his own master. Does the society determine the people, or do the people determine the society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of social model is critical. Governments, the structure of societies, are formed with these models. In fact, Marx believes that the purpose of creation of the models is to induce change: “The philosophers have only interpreted the world, in various ways; the point, however, is to change it.” The very belief in a model is potent enough to change how one thinks and interprets reality since a model employs a mode of thought. Marx says, “The materialist doctrine that men are products of circumstances and upbringing, and that, therefore, changed men are products of other circumstances and changed upbringing, forgets that it is men who change circumstances and that it is essential to educate the educator himself.” Our beliefs in models, which derive from our circumstances and our education, change society and hence other men. For Marx, the abstract model is tool to change reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marx’s idea of commodity fetishism is precisely such. Economics assumes that each individual desires to maximize economic value, that is, money. Then economic policy is implemented to maximize the wealth of the nation. The capitalist model assumes people want to maximize money, so when policy derived from this model is implemented, it will work most effectively when people actually pursue money as an end, thus people and governments will encourage such behavior in order for successful implementation of the policy. The result is that people seek money as the end, the objective marker that holds value. Hence, the implementation of a capitalist economic model has the propensity to induce consumerism. The implementation of theory affects how people act in practice. From this arises a great limitation in modeling human actions; societies are rarely static. A society changes through time, and old models lose accuracy. Interestingly enough, the creation of a model itself refashions society so that even more models are required as old models become outdated. The truth that the model tries to understand is changed by the adoption of the model itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adoption of a model can induce significant change and as such, we must be wary of the limitations of the model. In models wherein citizens determine the society, the resulting society is hard to predict, as citizens do not act uniformly. Free agents with negative liberty leads to chaos, in the sense that, the web of interaction between free agents is complex and unpredictable.	In models wherein the society determines the citizen, the goal is to create an ideal society, which in turn will create ideal citizens. Observe that once the model is based on the society, the success of the society becomes the end and not the success of the individual. The nature of this social model is to institutionalize, as individuals become a means to further the end of the institution. Of course, it is quite subjective whether the individual is more important or the collective, but pursuing the collective end requires the pursuit of a model society. Berlin says, “If we are not armed with an a priori guarantee of the proposition that a total harmony of true values is somewhere to be found, we must fall back on the ordinary resources of empirical observation and ordinary human knowledge.” The model has no guarantee of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, subscribing to a model that describes an ideal society remains attractive. Institutions have explicit goals and explicit paths to success within the models. There is security in belonging to an institution. Furthermore, even if an institution inhibits negative freedom, there is the stoic strategy of “retreat to the inner citadel.” The model has an objective, where if all the assumptions are correct, and all goes as planned, a utopia of sorts will be reached. A model with an assumed system of values, that is positive liberty, seems much more likely to achieve this utopia than the chaos of free agents all attempting to determine the objective of the society. However, Berlin is quick to warn, “This goes back to the naïve notion that there is only one true answer to every question: if I know the true answer and you do not, and you disagree with me, it is because you are ignorant; if you knew the truth, you would necessarily believe what I believe; if you seek to disobey me, this can be so only because you are wrong, because the truth has not been revealed to you as it has been to me. This justifies some of the most frightful forms of oppression and enslavement in human history.” In addition to the chance of the model failing, there is the possibility of the model being perverted. The silencing of the dialectic and the rule of one model is prone to unseemly manipulation. Positive freedom assumes a single set of values, but Berlin claims that there is a value pluralism, that is, “human goals are many, not all of them commensurable, and in perpetual rivalry with one another.” As such, one model cannot encompass the range of human behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem arises when we believe that only one model exists, that there is one ideal for all of humanity. We must break from the monolithic model. Value pluralism calls for a mirroring model pluralism. There is a symmetry between human and natural phenomena. Humans each desire their own goals, and every human has different goals which are sometimes in conflict with each other. Similarly, natural phenomena have their own models and each phenomena has its own model which are sometimes in conflict with each other. Furthermore, no model is truth by itself, just as there is not one ideal for all of humanity. Sartre poignantly says, “existence precedes essence.” For Sartre, life has no meaning a priori, but rather the individual creates his own set of values through action. We have seen that man creates models and that the implementation of those models can affect individuals, perhaps by changing their values. We each influence one another, which Sartre calls intersubjectivity: “this is the world in which man decides what he is and what others are.” We can freely create our own natures and break from any model imposed upon us. Let us then extend the mirror between human goals and models. Just as one human’s goals influence other humans’ goals, a model influences other models. Disciplines of science inform each other, much like a humans’ goals inform other humans’ goals. It is a dialectical process with thesis, antithesis, and synthesis. At this point, we have come full circle to Marx and his belief in Hegel’s dialectics. The synthesis creates a better model, which may appear to be the absolute model. However, as models are necessarily limited, we once again go through the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to have a social model that is watertight, we need to understand the human decision making process itself. Such efforts are being spearheaded by neuroscience and psychology, though a complete understanding seems very distant. Even if the universe followed a set of laws, the number of particles and their interactions would give rise to emergent unpredictable behavior. Despite our quite comprehensive understanding of physics, we are unable to predict weather accurately beyond a week because of its complexity. Likewise, the sheer number of neurons likely gives rise to incredibly complex phenomena, and we would require individual limited models for different phenomena in the brain. This highlights the eternal limitations of models, that even if we have the correct model of the universe, it will lead to complex behavior, complex enough that they demand their own models. These secondary models are limited in that they do not contain all the information of the first. Ultimately, the abstract networks of reason and causality that we create can never encompass the universe. All of our models are perpetually limited and can never be proven to be objective truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Models give us a false impression of complete understanding. We want to live under these models, because it is simpler. Goals, rules and hence, the path towards success are explicit. For the most part, the advanced models we have developed, accurately portray reality. But models are not truth, or else one model would reveal the fallacies inherent in the every other model. Instead the dialectic of these models reveals the fallacies of each theory. Then whatever we choose to be the prevailing model is the model whose fallacies we are most ignorant of. Models are useful for making predictions that inform an action, but since the model is limited, one should not live by a model. In fact, even the mere implementation, or belief of a model affects thought. These models inform our conscious, but it would seem that we cannot live solely by a simple universal code of ethics or a universal meaning of life, for these models are perpetually limited.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">The rules of causality and reason, by which the universe apparently operates, are represented as models. The apparent order of phenomena in reality is condensed into an abstract representation in an attempt to predict and offer insight into reality. However, human actions seem particularly resistant to models. There are a plethora of models postulating the possible nature of human, human’s end, and the nature of societies, but they conflict with each other. Through this dialectic, a new model is made, perhaps closer to the objective truth, but the model, being an entity in the intelligible world and not the sensible world, can never encompass complete objective truth. Though models are undeniably useful in understanding reality, we must consider the limitations of models and the consequences of our models failing.</summary></entry></feed>